welcome everybody thanks for tuning in
to this dialogue with John Verve a key
my latest one we've had a bunch of them
and as always they are ecstatic they
usually end up very very ecstatic so
this was no exception so before I give
more context with that with this video
here's some housekeeping circling
Institute my company we have an online
training coming up that's open for
registration we have a weekend course
coming up online which is July eleventh
and twelfth and we have a open evening
every Thursday night so links the
circling Institute below if you are
interested in working with me one on one
I am I am taking private clients so go
ahead and email me my emails below okay
so so this conversation is a
this one really is uh we we cover like
initially what I wanted to get the
download on on one of an event that he
ran right which would choose
experimenting with dialog was I think it
was on rebel wisdom in it and of course
we start talking about that and we start
talking about the the notion of dialog
owes and you can really feel in this
conversation for me the the process of
do logos in it becoming distinct as a as
a practice right the terms are starting
to really find themselves and things are
starting to get more articulate but but
it's it's funny because it's been very
fractal because it's in it's been
through with the very process right
the very process that is being created
is done by the process itself and
there's something so telling about that
so we go deep into that and then we just
really start to get into some really
really like at the edge of
intelligibility kinds of things about
like well what is this all what's the
substance of a dialogue and dialogue oh
s--- right and go into that like what's
what's the backdrop of that and for me
what i really kind of came out came out
of this with a very i don't know a sense
of that was really humming for me and is
humming for me is just this sense of
what Tillich talks about which is how
how the individual right is eight is is
the holding of attention between the
mystery of individuation and full
participation that tension between those
two is is really how we develop it's how
we connect and how that goes and why
that is and what it's connected to is
connected to the micro into the macro
and and and really is a it connects us
to two dimensions of the divine the
sacred the beyond the
beyond us and in the sense of reverence
one and awe one gets touched with in a
relationship right or what's possible in
relationship in conversations in
dialectic dialogue dialogue OHS and
circling so enjoy all right
the welcome John good to see you again
yeah it's always good to see you I just
did you actually just did your um Wow it
looks like I'm really opening us the
result of my meditation look I just came
from John's class the the beginning of
the of the Tai Chi Chuan that yeah I
love I'm I'm really loving the way that
you're layering it it's like the lay the
just the layering in itself has just
been insightful about the way it works
together and the one the one that was
really evocative for me and he's been
has been lingering with me was when was
when you went
alright Praja and Metta right in breath
right proje out-breath Metta yeah
in the figure-ground in that sense at
some point they'll interpenetrate each
other I was just like that just it it it
not only just was the experience cuz it
wasn't like it wasn't experiencing that
before but it made something distinct
and that distinction has been popping up
everywhere right yeah just that layering
of those things over the course of time
just in themselves is a yields yields
insight thank you that's uh yeah that's
what I learned from my teachers they
called you practice so yeah
sorry for interrupting years I just
wanted to make sure that just people are
listening they the turn so that yeah be
it the when you're doing the in-breath
you feel your chest expanding you're
doing Metta called the plate of practice
we're exhaling you're doing the pasta
and then like if she said in proximity
you're alternating between men and the
past night and then at some point it
goes from instead of being out and in
and out any and it goes to being like
you said all at once injury management
project that are non-dualistic a very
active and dynamic non-dualistic state
yeah that is very conducive for
transformation right and then yeah so
yeah
then you recognize that because this
idea of Bill like layering practices on
each other into an ever-growing ecology
that was that was the deep lesson that I
got from the people who taught me
because I was taught the pasta and meta
and Tai Chi Chuan together and so yeah
now that we've done much more I guess
more than more than often is that much
more embodied forms of the past doesn't
matter and then taking them into Praja
now we're turning as you said towards
the the Tai Chi Chuan direction I'm
teaching people Jack Jong which is
standing and each one movement these are
parts of Chi kung the cultivation of the
chief and that's also to layer back on
because if you've probably noticed that
a lot of these exercises and now
inactive and active image imaginal
exercises yes
we're enacting beginning right the
expansion like respective bars now the
yin the centering and and then again
what happens is when you get sort of the
Chi experience you get that again
neither in or out right neither move nor
at rest
it's beyond all of that and then that
and the prize not starting to do this
with each other yes that's the whole
point the whole point is to give it the
layering that's the mutual of 40 is to
create a
in structure that will take on a life of
its own yeah it is
and it's interesting like so when we
went into the Tai Chi Chuan it was just
from those layers again it was just one
of those things okay here's the out at
the end and and it in that hole it just
starts to hit these these built up
layers of distinctions and anchors that
are in the body right it's just it's
it's really great I'm really
appreciating it Jen I know a lot of
other people are too well thank you yeah
there's more like for example the first
Jack the Gen John we did it of embracing
the tree right and then they go in the
review on Wednesday and Friday you know
that that's also connects to you know
the core for from a personal year he
should your center then you route it
like a tree right and so the embracing
of the tree is the participatory knowing
of you know what it's like to be a tree
almost a perspective on annoyance and so
yeah there's lots there's lots going on
it's meant to be like music it's meant
to be layered vertically in harmony and
then layered like you know horizontally
like in melody and so the melody and the
harmony the musicality of
intelligibility is being exported and
enhanced you know articulated and
afforded process so interesting so yeah
so interesting in and also the electio
Davina like just that that sense of
bringing all those ways of knowing into
into like basically an idea like a poem
into a distinction right they have how
all that fits together and one of the
things I wanted to you know what it's
tough
once you think they want to talk with
you I wanted to talk with you about your
experienced
taking the group into dialogue oh s---
at the wisdom I talk about lectio Divina
and it's in the sense of what we talked
about last time how and I've been
thinking about this since we talked
about it which you
your prediction that once people start
doing
lectio divina in the in a group that
there's something about that just makes
sense that then left naturally open it
into dialo goes right and that's
actually had me think about about what's
happening with when you read a text
right and then what's happening when we
look at that like translate that into
dialogue osore dialogue when it goes
into dialo goes right of of you know
who's what's the text right who's the
reader right like what's the meaning of
the text and start to play with those
metaphors yeah well I'm happy to talk
about all of this lecture is an example
a really important example of what I
call a bridging practice and the ecology
practices so there are practices like
we've just we're talking where you can
layer them on to each other and then
they interpenetrate and the HR for but
then there's also practices that are
designed to bridge between other
practices and so the way I see in
practice lexy oh is it takes you from
the silence of a synod practice and
gives you into speech but a kind of
speech that then prepares you as you're
saying for dia logos which is inter
speech right
and so lexeme for me is this really
living bridge between the logos and
meditation and contemplation between
logos and progeny if you were to ask me
for sort of the ontological designations
yeah right
so Praja what is project actually and
what does it mean again what does it
indicate
so it's wisdom ya know but but in
in this sense I was crying about this
when I was tied with Andrew and Chris
and away this or integrates aristotle's
nation to both Sophia and phronesis
right it's so it's it's it's an active
dynamic it's when your fluid
intelligence the intelligence in action
in interaction right is because has
become a self liberating so that dynamic
of being so organizing right is self
organize it's autopoietic a minute
yourself organized to sneak out right
away in which its self transcendence
self liberating it's when you're being
free from foolishness parasitic
processing but you also be freed for
free free to connect more deeply so and
proj not so that's its functionality its
phenomenology is that it's a state that
emphasizes I would say there's upon
traditional language so literally I'm
speaking I think the non duality that is
traditional is a way of for grounding
the trunk the trenched activity the
coupled Ness
the dynamical emergence of agent and
arena and so that the point about cross
them especially you see you see it the
way I presented in the course as the
stereoscopic fusion of meta
contemplation and meditation what what
it's actually doing right is it's it's
sort of putting you in a space and so in
that I I'm becoming aware of that
matches mental moding right and then the
past not I'm moving to a place of dis
identification that makes insight
possible so I get the deepest possible
insights from the pasta but what are
they reef
fracturing well they're restructuring
what meta is making available to me
which is my existential mode so I'm not
getting intellectual in saying I'm
getting an existential insight but it's
not a one moment insight it's like in
the flow state I'm getting a cascade of
existential insights that have that
aspirational trajectory yeah that yeah
that feedback loop yep
so except it's like with Praja is
something like it's wisdom I keep
getting the sense as you were talking
about the sense of this this affording
of and for some reason I was thinking
about apprehension and comprehension
like yeah but it's like it's very
perceptive
but it's but notice the word you use
apprehension so why had this I this term
for prehension right which is the way so
how your mind perceives the world is
your mind doesn't really perceive
because you mind picks up on our
relations and patterns that are actually
not visible or audible or tactile you're
pretending the real relations and then
you're perceiving the real things right
and so progeny is both prehension and
perception right yes it may be that
inner penetration of the two right yeah
so dojin says so you're in the state
that's beyond in and out it's beyond in
the sense of beyond and beneath its
beyond and beneath in and out it's
beyond and beneath mind and body
it's beyond and beneath it self and
others it's beyond the beneath God and
nature yeah in Lexi oh and you bring
that into the Dharma you bring that into
look like the wisdom teachings as a way
of reading not for information but
reading to entrust yourself to
transformation yeah
so that gets you into like linking all
the kinds of knowing together and then
you take that into a little bit and
that's what I need if we can get all of
the if we can expect you can get what I
described in Praja right presencing
itself within dia logos yeah got
something I think Victor sound totally
and it's also it's also in terms of you
know in terms of practices it seems like
that those the linking right between
those and because you know that it's
that common thing of that you always
hear about of like where people can
meditate really well but they get up in
the moment somebody you know it doesn't
give them what they want they they it
all goes away there's something about I
think that dialogue owes seems to just
bring just a sense of like bring that
into the realm of of interaction and how
we go about the world right exactly and
so Lexi o is bring you into interaction
right with other people's viewpoints and
words and ideas and then right and then
things like the cheek on practices right
designed to bring you into physical
interaction with your environment and do
logos is to bring you into interpersonal
and also ultimately inter ontological
yeah your actions right right and so
yeah I that's why and you've seen some
when I teach I teach that how can come
out of your sitter practice is a part of
the practice in fact I think it's the
most important part of the practice exam
that's why I give people another
bridging practice which is the reciting
of the five promises to yourself as a
way of bridging because you should
always be thinking of your sitting not
as an escape not as a vacation but as an
education it's always meant to be
integrated as much as possible with your
everyday consciousness cognition and
communitas everyday right
so to come to that there's a point about
that I get this question often and it's
a good question that's why I'm happy to
answer it people will have to ask how I
how do I know that I'm doing it right
and what they mean is they want some
sort of some phenomenological marker
that says hey you're doing it right
yeah that's what we love yeah what you
actually look is the integration
happening are the patterns in your
practice are they starting to emerge
naturally in your life and then as name
and especially other people notice it
right right and if then and there and
does that mean that the pattern there
right that the patterns in your life are
also no coming up in your practice yeah
yes when when you get the reciprocal
opening that's when you know you're
doing it right there isn't anything in I
mean I can give people guy which I do I
answer a question you know well if you
do like if your mind is getting really
dull and comfy you're not doing it well
you can help people but at the level of
am I doing this virtuously because
that's what people are all totally out
like not am I just practicing it sort of
efficiently but am I ultimately
cultivating wisdom and virtue is a well
you know it's it's it's in the
integration that's why the layering and
the linking the layering practices and
the linking of practices is so vital
right so vital and and one see I'm
getting very passionate about this one
of the things I'm deeply critical of is
the oversimplification of these kind of
practices in the West when we take all
of mindfulness think about the Buddha
gave this Eightfold Path it is
comprehensive of people's lives and then
we reduce all of that to you sort of the
mindfulness aspects and then we reduce
all of the mindfulness to sitting in
meditation and then we think that this
is going to accomplish this the same
thing as this entire ecology practices I
think I think that's a mistake
yeah see that's a total mistake yeah so
this this
this sense of where I think you've
talked about this before about where
that that that self-organization right
the the flow of that though the the the
logos of it right to begins to take hold
and gets a life of its own that shows it
shows up and you're listening it shows
up right and this is what I'm thinking
about with with daya logos is is that
there's a way where we're exercising in
dialogue oasiz like a practice right
but then there's dialo goes in
relationship with your own internal
world and the way that you think and the
way that you relate to reality and in
that that sense of this is where it gets
really exciting to look at that logos as
a practice right yeah so it seems got a
little bit breakthrough actually well
Kristin I've been doing a lot of work
and I've been doing and then I've also
been doing I trained you as a cognitive
scientist and it comes off with a little
bit arrogant but I hope it's not which
is you know I have to try and understand
something by reverse engineering it
right and so as you know and with your
help when Peters know Chris's help they
join so right I've been taking a deep
look and I'm continue to do so at the
help of many people like that's always a
whole bunch of people more like what was
the ancient practice of dialectic first
of all when when you as you as you
follow forward especially when you
followed into the neoplatonist dialectic
goes from dialectic is simultaneously
interpersonal but like you said it's
also interpersonal and it's in Toronto
logical with people are moving within
the layers here we go yet with the
layers of their ontology and they're
also right so in Chris and I and have
used the metaphor of the interpersonal
being up here horizontal dimension and
intra ontological being the vertical
dimension and
so just one more thing just it might be
helpful for people I'm finding it
helpful when Chris and I are really
trying to make this because I want to
bring out something you brought you made
there because I've been thinking about
this a lot and maybe one careful with
our Terms it could help ya notice like
we were talking about the difference
between when you do something you do a
practice but especially we do it in a
layered and linked way right the
self-organization can even become
autopoietic right it can take on a life
of its own yes yes so I'm trying to
reserve the term dialectic for practices
that I can do even layering and Lincoln
and then do logos for when it takes when
the practice does that share it takes on
its own right right so the way I now try
to say it is I practice dialectic to
realize the Ilocos yeah yeah okay that
makes sense yeah it's like putting the
logs of the propositions yeah yes
lighting and like you get him you start
rubbing them together and I like
dialogue dialectic and at some point it
just sparks right it does the grater
yeah yeah you're making use of all kinds
of carrots idea and absolutely and so at
revel wisdom I got to practice with
people mostly what I would call the
horizontal image dialectic
but I was also able to start bringing in
a bit of the vertical although a lot of
the vertical also needs to be done by
individuals on their own but but I was
getting both of those and what was
interesting was also to see like where
and when right as to use your metaphor
it sparks and catches fire and you can
see people started to get caught up yeah
and so part of the engineering was to
think well we already know some of the
conditions that will get people into the
flow state and the flow state is when I
practice something and then it takes on
don't be catch inspired right so I was
trying to bring that
and then I mean and and I talked about I
made reference to all of you guys I
remember was repeatedly because that
what I've been trying to do is go over
and you know Chris and I are doing sort
of very high level theory and then I'm
doing very I don't know level but what
rounded practice and then and part of
that practice has been to constantly
review all of what we've been doing from
what I've learned from you what I've
learned from you know other people and
trying to draw it together into a fairly
doable layering and linking of practices
that what I call dialectic that gets us
into dialogo so yeah and I mean if you
wanted some point I could go over what
that looks like concretely what happened
what happened at level wisdom at least
from my perspective was it was it was
very successful because there was one
more sort of term of the theoretical
wheel that happened just before rebel
wisdom and it came up in my discussion
with you you remember our last one is
you know that the fact that all the
Platonic dialogues are about virtue is
not a coincidence yeah because virtue is
the place in which all of these things
come together and that yeah so that the
that the dialectic if it's trying to
come to you logos should always be both
trying should have virtue as a topic
while exemplifying virtue as a response
to that top of there yeah and so what
happened I'll just go through what it
looks like now again I I was clear I had
to present a truncated thing because I
see this is actually something that
should people should do after they've
done right meditation contemplation
spice each one and circulate after done
those four things I think before they do
this great but I complain what am I
going to do Wow before I teach you I
couldn't do it
I had the presence
this right but I want that now I can say
it we've got some primary export like
people they used to have to be doing a
meditative practice a contemplative
practice of moving mindfulness practice
and they have to be doing circling those
are the things they have to be doing
alright now let's say that that is given
okay that's a big given I get it but
let's say let's presume that that's the
case
so then how it works right is that sorry
one more thing which was coming up also
in the discussion from Andrew Chris or
if you're doing this maybe this is right
on the edge of my thinking and there's
all these people that are helping me
right now and I want everybody included
right yeah yeah the other thing is which
is how do we bring in something how do
we make it most accredit and how do we
bring in argumentation yeah okay so a
treble wisdom I couldn't fully bring in
the argumentation I'll talk about how he
did that recently I rub a wisdom it goes
like there's some people you break them
up into groups of four okay and this is
influenced by more Bateson's ideas of
one date and the warm data labs right so
what happens is that group they decide
collectively what virtue is going to be
their topic let's say sorry yeah okay so
what happens is one person it goes first
and the person picks somebody who's
going to be their initial amplifier and
so the first and you don't make
proposition you make proposals you know
what state propositions you commit your
stuff to a proposal and they need it in
both ways not only do you grasp the
semantic content but you mean it like
when you ask somebody did you mean what
you just said okay you committed to it
okay so full meaning so that's why I say
say I propose that don't say honesty is
think I propose that like so I propose
that honesty is X okay and then the
amplifier their job is stuff and this is
like from the few person the past
exercise and what you'll see circling
right and they just see why certain
would really matter to this person who's
amplifying they're not supposed to in
any way challenge at the amplifications
they what they do is they well I notice
that when you when you when you first
talked about
honesty you were leading forward you're
leaning back and you know you know is in
my mind for there is you because that's
what you do you do that you notice what
people are doing
you know this their gesture and this is
also came from the work I did um the
focusing well you clenched your hand
there go back let your hand what's that
light what's going on free right now
right yeah and so can you tell me more
and oh you were started there what's
happening where you're smiling so though
the amplifiers trying to get the person
to become more reflectively aware of
their participation in the proposal a I
pray to amplify amplify amplify mm-hmm
then at some point the proposal is the
proposer is going to get towards kind of
an Emporium right yeah and then and then
and what happens is you know and now the
amplifier through speaks it switches to
what I call appreciation the amplifier
has the first thing what they what they
really got right so they have to repeat
back to the person who spoke this is
what I heard you saying and they have to
do that until the first person says yeah
you got me you understood
so appreciation the sense of
understanding and then and then this is
what I value about what you said this is
what is good isn't what but this is what
I hadn't bought it before this is what I
had forgotten right so they do that they
do the appreciation okay right then they
are going to turn to another third
person what they're going to do is
they're going to do anticipation of
their proposal they don't jump into
their proposal and what they do is they
have to say this is where they are now
challenging but they're not going to
actually confront the person they're
gonna write so what they're gonna say is
okay this is what I thought was missing
in that proposal well here's a part of
honesty that I really think is important
that was missing or here's what was
mysterious in that proposal I found that
strange or odd right and then finally
and I emphasize people don't put the
emphasis on this one you're not trying
to be right you're trying to come into
right
relationship yeah yeah right yeah you
know either attack neither merely
attacking nor merely agreeing what this
is the mistake and I try to break it
back up and de mistaken what how the
proposition is wrong but is there an
assumption is there a way the person was
taking yes you want to call into
question okay talk about that for a bit
and now the other third person amplifies
the second person during the
anticipation right right and then until
the until that that second person can
now say okay now I'm ready I propose
that honesty is this and then they get
amplified and then at some point they
stop and then the third person does the
appreciation with them and then turns to
the fourth and does anticipation until
they make a proposal and then it cycles
all the way around on the floor so you
do that until everybody does this yeah
and you get groups groups that come back
would it be good to at least have four
groups right to come back to do a common
space and and hopefully usually almost
always they've done different virtues
good honesty right never you like when
you're amplifying you're trying to pick
up on how the person is exemplifying not
just Expo doing exposition I raised over
right and because it's virtual people it
really bridges for people you know the
four groups come back and now they're
all together and now this is what they
answer they don't answer in closure but
this is what they been going to do Louis
you ask them what is virtue - what is
honesty yeah what is courage and what
happens is they do the thing where they
exhume into their particular virtue and
event and then zoom in and zoom in and
zoom out zoom in and zoom out yeah
happens right if they get into they get
into deal logos and they get a sense of
right they get a sense of the mourners
and the Dutchman's that they their
virtuous thorough complex and dynamic
and they feel that they've come into a
better relationship and then and I
didn't have time to do that that I like
what you could do is you could just have
open reflection after that process
or you know I thought that there might
be another transitional thing where
people go back just into circling and
they just go back into circling then
they that's all just resonating and
vibrating for them yeah that's how the
process turns yeah that's interesting so
that's the horizontal but you see how to
bid it and had a bit of the vertical in
it right right yeah absolutely I like
that that sense of starting with
something like virtues particular
virtues and then the meta idea that
unites those right and going in between
structurally that just seems really
deeply penetrated yeah what I want to
say right now it's really important to
me because I care about you I care about
your work I hope you see your influence
in all of this I hope you see I'm trying
to incorporate a lot of what I've
learned to you and try to do it justice
I hope you feel that oh yeah Oh totally
yeah yeah that's important to me yeah I
really I really do I really do big-time
okay and I feel that too I feel that in
our in our friendship in our in the way
that you you continually note it but
also just in the the fact of the mutual
kind of penetration of these ideas and
you know like we're constantly talking
on text and and it's a it's a it's a
that's how it lives for me when you do a
great job boy I saw that
interpenetration well I didn't see it I
heard it I listened to you when you were
on my discord server thank you for doing
that by the way that was wonderful
all right so so anyways you like it Matt
I'm not like again imagine individuals
who were doing like the mindfulness
ecology meditation contemplation moving
economy the Tai Chi there and then as
you said then they bridge the magnet
Alexia yeah they grouped Lexia
maybe out of that a particular virtue
right it comes up right and then they
take that into view logos right right
you have that whole yeah would just be
very very powerful for people Holly
absolutely any if you think about it to
it be if you you run a few of those and
then just think about like okay so how
would that just catch when somebody just
starts to talk about their life yes yeah
and like you don't even have to I would
imagine you don't even have to put many
frames around it after a few cycles of
those people are probably just you'll
probably notice that people go it's
they're amplifying they start doing all
the components right yeah totally
totally and and I would hope that they
would also start to notice how the
various practices inter for each other
right then we start to listen to people
are speaking more both more poetically
yeah and then the mindfulness to bear
because one of the promises we make is
promise like to use speech mindfully
carefully lovingly write free and so Oh
but as I'm listening like does this
person like it's Lexi Oh Davina I'm also
practicing the mindfulness and then they
they're also like looking for what but
what is being exemplified here what
verse she was coming again I could see
but that that is what happens right yeah
and then the point is we we get right
not just propositions we get the
proposals of ways of being gracious and
ways of life being exemplified so now
the more recent piece I did and this is
something I'm you know I want to talk to
you about and but and it was it's just
come out on Andrews channel it will come
out of my channel on Friday is how'd it
mean something like argumentation in and
so what I was thinking is instead of
just a sequence of propositions but what
it is is it's a sequence of proposals
right that logos that gather together
and you
can we afford each other until right
right and then what you do is you
basically make a proposal and then you
do some dice via locals about it and
then the person makes another proposal
what you might let them do is what I did
is for to present the the sequence of
proposals and then you go back and do
via logos and you try and sort of jazz
away from one proposal to the next right
they all come to belong together and
mutually afford right so that's what I
did so I had a particular argument but
the argument I was making an argument
that virtue is the beauty of wisdom and
what that means and how to understand
that and then what I did was I had a
sequence of proposals and then and then
we did we did sort of be a logos around
and so you do feel like if you allow me
this metaphors around each proposal and
then between each proposal let this gets
into ateva a kind of you know positive
proposals where you're seeing all the
proposals in each and each and all right
right approach to proposals yes I'm
seeing t-shirts that's awesome
well it's also the thing that you just
laid out there I mean on some level I
bet I mean you're exemplifying I mean
isn't this is what what you've been
doing on in all your discussions right
is you've been doing just that or you
kind of have an idea and you're playing
with it right like even before all all
of this was specifically formulated like
the way that you did but it seems like
that's what I sense is that you there's
something that kind of emerges and you
have an idea maybe it's this and this
and this like oh yeah and then we go
into dialogue about it right and another
something if something happens and it
puts the next thing so if like we just
watched all of the discussions I wonder
I bet we at least we see that pattern
that goes throughout I think so I think
that's exactly right and that's I mean
that has been sort of the teacher
guiding me and in this whole process
basically Prime and see what
patterns are taking shape yeah right
what principles are coming into process
vada those patterns and what processes
are being principled in those patterns
and seeing all of that working together
so that's what I keep looking for well
you know here's a pattern yeah look what
principle is it bringing in and what
process is it really you - well here's a
pattern what process is it bring equal
is it is it is it explicate and bringing
a normativity you know so I always think
of this emanation of principle when this
invert it's a process and that and the
logos is the patterning right so that's
what that's what I'm looking for yes
sort of the method I use what I'm trying
to get a sense about this and then and
then as a cognitive scientist what I do
is a reverse engineer I say what do I
know about human cognition yeah right
and how could I think how could I
articulate these practices yeah such
that I could I could reverse it right
that's what I've been doing
totally yeah absolutely and so it's
interesting like as it's coming out it's
as you're formulating it right it's
interesting there's that sense of
there's that sense of in a certain sense
like like I'm bringing it like more to
your awareness right now well isn't that
what you've been doing on some level all
the way through it's like here's that
that thing about then you talk about the
teacher right that deaf that invisible
deft hand that's that on one level it
looks like I was thinking about this
with with with rapport the difference
between creating rapport and then the
experience of rapport is is more like
it's revealed right it's like yes
there's always that sense of like when
I'm in a rapport with somebody one you
find yourself into it but it's not this
sense of like I have created something
something it's more like oh there you
are it's like oh I think that's right
and that I mean that's so Chris and I
well you've read the chapter and that's
in and we talked about this as the
movement from logos little al to logos
all right so the idea here is right the
more nests of intelligibility logos with
all the way read the logos that
ultimately is part of on toast but what
was a being right that's always
precipitated into right it's impregnated
into our spoken or are spoken logos and
our gestural logos ladies right and so
what would right and then what we do in
the deal logos is we like it's the
conception but the pregnancy is right
it's developed and the Midwife ER and
then what you're doing is you're giving
birth to the logos but it actually finds
you and you and I talked about this and
that that's what the virtue comes in
because Richie was ultimately right
every virtue is a way of being wise in a
particular situation it's a way of a
finding the logos in speech act and the
logos of being and so that's that's that
was my attempt to disclose because I was
talking to Chris about this I say guy is
always doing that and that's not a
complaint by the way guys always doing
that where he say look at how we got
here a place we couldn't get to on our
own but it's but what we discovered was
always there that's why I point I
brought that got term inventio yeah
right right yeah the areas is in the
book on Augustine's invention of the
inner self this inventio means both to
make and to discover all right and it's
that sense so what I think it is is
again like the way dialectic makes
possible but it isn't the making of the
Ilocos right I think the via logos the
dialogue partner moguls between us right
right that that that that's the making
part but what is discovered right
already they're almost absolutely absent
conceals that whole thing about like
concealed and revealed in the hiddenness
yes is that is not that not the you know
the Castel hiddenness of where it's like
you conquer everything and then you even
conquer hidden this right it's more like
the hiddenness is what we follow the
whole time
right and when it reveals see this is
the thing about it like I think one of
the things I love about Rilke and
cult-like poetry really is it has this
ability to reveal you could say the
unknown without without making it known
but it retains its unknown it's
mysterious mysteriousness in its
disclosure right so it becomes great so
so I think about this as a trajectory of
transformation that always stems met and
i'm aguii right so the logos deep
dynamic unfolding of the logos gives us
a sense of trajectory in a
transformation but that ultimately is a
finger that's pointing towards the logos
right metonymically it's it's not
separate from it
it's a metonym it participates in it but
it also points beyond itself in its
participation this is so Neoplatonic
right so that's that's so I think of the
movement that happens both the movement
out of my own subjectivity into the we
space right and then right and then and
then the movement of that whole space
right that don't that trend by
trajectory that's that's me that's us me
and us pointing with our whole being
right towards the logos but the ability
to point embodies the logos which that's
not being separate from it yes exactly
exactly exactly
in that sense of of where you meet you
in that I really liked your last video
with Chris and and Andrew is it not
Andrew yeah Andrew sweet yeah um where
you guys are talking about yeah I think
you said something and it kind of in
passing but it kind of struck me of of
where how Platanos puts the you know the
meta logos right it's all kind of like
in this in this infinite all at once
this right yes we have to basically take
that in dialogue owes and bring that
into sequence
yes that that's that's the function of
soul yeah that's the patinas that's soul
takes what it so intellect is the all at
once miss right like how each mercs you
actually presupposes the other virtues
and then right so if I'm going to be
honest I also have to be courageous
all right right if I'm gonna be honest
right I also need to know how to be kind
right because right because if I'm just
honest without kindness I'm not actually
honest I'm just brusque you're cool and
so right and then you can think about
how each virtue is just like they say
how do I be wise in this here madness
well to be wise here now is to be
courageous to be wise here now is to be
kind to being wise here now is to be
level together so tight as that's new
that's the news that the insular right
all the Vern I'll the principles of
intelligibility all the virtues are
there he often compares them like if
like theorems in an argument and this is
why Spinoza is so important they all all
interpenetrate in to define all at once
that's news and then news like that all
at once and it's that one
the the one e-mini points to what the
one right totally
it points up towards the one but as you
said it also it's also it emanates it
affords it makes possible the die annoy
I yeah the guy anyway is the know yet
but it's in motion right right daya neue
and that real local are right and that's
all and so what happens that's what
we're talking about in that in both that
dialogue in the previous one what soul
is the mediator between muchness sort
between more nests and sections yeah how
we participate in the inexhaustible
right yes yes how that comes into the
non categorical non-repeatable here
nowness right like the sort of the
mystery at the court of time yeah yes
yeah he split into you relationship the
mystery at the core of the turn
mystery of participation and the mystery
of individuation are brought into
relationship to each other like that
yeah like like like oh it's almost like
this is deeper sense of space and time
mutually penetrating each other right
yes yes yeah evidence and emergence and
time yes this stuff I'm the working on
energy no right now it's so important
because that he he's the guy that turns
dialectic yeah right into a like a
metaphysical principle he sees reality
in in this kind of you laconic dollar
hero Gina
arrow Gina yes here's a really good
introductory book this one right here Oh
John SCOTUS oh yes okay yes yes cuz he's
doing that in this hole yeah I mean
that's exactly what he's and he did it
he is way before his time right because
he's way before he has something much
more comprehensive intransitive and the
interesting thing is the person P on the
division of nature is actually written
as a dialogue yeah actually it's
presented as a dialogue and it's
interesting because it's presented as an
interpersonal dialogue between two
people right basically the Guru and the
student right but it's also there's four
parts the four division so it's also an
ontological dialogue or four divisions
alright well if it's heat and he's it
exemplifies like turning what we're
talking about into on one pole a
comprehensive way of life and on the
other pole a corresponding the
comprehensive worldview actually yeah
that's amazing so this is also kind of
gets to another kind of thing that I was
I was I've been thinking about as well
is you thinking about like okay so what
and I think he said it when it when you
when you said soul is that is that is
that is the mediator between these two
which had brought me to the it reminds
me of this thing I've been I think I
texted you about it - what's it with
Chris about like well we look at it well
what is what is the medium like medium
of this and I started to think about
play with that about you know like in
painting right oil painting great and
what like in this and a certain sense of
like in it's the right medium in
comparison because like acrylic
I can't work with acrylic because it it
does basically the same thing it's hard
to tell the difference once it's all dry
but it's you can't it it's too
constraining with time right so you have
to like you know with oil it stays wet
so you you can really have you can paint
it you can blend the colors and work
with it on the canvas versus on the you
know have it ready-made and then painted
in and then I was thinking about what a
medium does right the oil does is it a
one level it holds everything together
right it holds the paint together right
but in holding it together it also
releases it into appearance but yet the
museum itself to the degree that it's
doing its job when it releases the paint
into appearance while holding it
together it also saw itself
simultaneously withdrawals into that
release with right yes and so I just
think about like what so what would be
the oil right of the dialogical dialogue
owes painting you know and it's
interesting to kind of think about that
right well I think I think I do too
let's do it let's see what this is this
is what I kind of came up with it I was
thinking about like well I think what
probably makes it what did what it is is
that that some level the realization
right of the dialogue into dial OSA
right is is actually where where that
which withdrawals on some level in in
the oil it goes through it realizes
itself in in like kind of a trance
substation right or something like that
like it's like it's like it's almost
like the the medium is the always
already the case the invisible deft hand
that on some level at the top kind of
goes ah make sense you know on some
level I think that's right a nominal
logically it's about these about the
about what we talked about the both you
know phenomena The Shining port that's
always the broad functionally the other
the other time to you the other thing it
also has me think about like well okay
well well what is the medium though
right what is the phenomenon right and
this is where I start to touch it when I
feel into that I started I started to
touch into Nick how do you say it to
shaman coming yeah this sense of
emptiness of there's something about
that as well so the emptiness that I
think is yeah okay so I want to say so
I'll propose over here and then we'll
look for convergence will do the
argument there you go because I think
the medium the thing that glues like the
paint but also becomes transparent so we
proceed through it I think it's
relevance realization because radiation
does is it makes the framing that then
withdraws precisely because it's
transparent and I want to be looking
through it right right because precisely
because I've seen by means of it it
draws into right into your and grounding
of intelligibility and then but you have
to remember the relevance realization
isn't mine right it's a
the world and we are Co emerging
together yeah so I think the emptiness
is the fact of this deep coupling the
coupling that's at the mystery of my
fleshiness
which is what you know in a lot of
Buddhist facts you get the sense of you
know the pure mind which is the mind
that isn't is is the the existing power
to become any particular form but is no
form itself that's that's relevance
realization and that that mystery of the
sense of such Ness right is what keeps
me coupled to the off in love with the
more nests of reality so the more
earnest the combinatorial explosion of
information
yeah right and the ongoing open-ended
that's the emptiness no essence to it
the open endedness of the relevance
realization this mystery of the Sukkoth
they come together right they come
together in my framing of the world that
and the emptiness is the mystery of the
morning the combinatorial explosive
nature reality the mystery of the
suchness the open endedness at the
open-ended evolution of my role of
relevance realization and those are the
two couple together in that in that in
taking your proposal right so the the so
relevance realization is what you're
proposing is the medium of this right
yes is relevance realization and what I
what in it it's and in you could say the
the background the more like the the
background is like the emptiness right
and and in the foreground is the
suchness right yeah I would say that or
exactly how you said it I would say I
would say that the background is the
section it's the background is you want
opacity for individuation the capacity
for here now thicken yourself to the
situation yeah but the world is not the
world impregnates each situation but
it's all
is more than any situation yeah oh yeah
so this is always reinventing itself
right in the in the face of the world
always unpacking itself always be more
both diachronic Lee and synchronically
those horizontally and vertically and
then and then relevance realization but
is the process of that being realized
over and over and over and over again
that's why I use the word realization
yes simultaneously like detection and
adaptive fitting and it's also
actualization and coming you to be in
I'm trying to get both the subjective
and objective poles of this process by
using the word realization totally cuz
it's like it's like there cuz the
realization I really got the sense of
like this is why it's the media because
the realization it's like what what I'm
hearing you say is what's realized that
immediately brings everything together
and then you ask like well what's
realized right what is the real is it
what realized this realization right and
you look back you end up back there but
just in that process I there's a sense
of how world making that is exactly
exactly this is ultimately right it's
about how things stand I don't exist
within being where being is the right
the intelligibility that reaches through
the horizons of intelligibility totally
and that was yes so and so and then of
course naturally it's like what's that
glow beyond the horizon and then you end
up back you and so in some level you you
in in moving towards that glow and
realizing it the thing that yeah this is
why it's the the individuation this is
why we're so like just to keep it you
know this is we're still in the
amplification part I think right like of
like yeah yep that's important right
thinking about Tillich like the perfect
like a participation individuation
tension right it's like how this is mere
I hang honestly you're frozen
to sell everything oh let's see
okay back you back a cool cool right
yeah I just try to beat the gestures are
so important right yeah that sense of
that there's that quality of where when
you when you have a passion for
something right and you you just engage
with it in some sense it's like there is
there's that experience of where you're
not thinking about yourself however at
some point you it's a KO Constitution
where you're in your face elated by what
you've been looking at right and then
you realize you realize the whole time
that it's been this mutually shaping
yeah well and that's Christopher
Christopher more but more the Socratic
self-knowledge
that's his basic argument he says that
what Socrates tried to show people is
that the the truest deepest kind of
self-knowledge is not gained through
introspection not gained through right
it's not the intuition it's not gain
some sort of formal definition it's game
through how like your commitment and
participation in what you just described
that that's where you actually know
yourself that's why the sabbatic self is
inherently aspirational it's not the
romantic self right you're not
expressing it out right what's happening
is it's being induced from you as the
world it is how you how your whole
emergence commits to the coherence of
the world of faithfulness the love that
that's where you truly find out who you
are
right Wow so the whole point about
Socratic right self-knowledge
is you cannot find it except in deal
logos and but conjoint of that is that's
where you deeply most truly find out who
you are
yes through yes through like what I'm
really kind of getting is like it's a
it's almost a pop you can't be a
Cartesian oh right like I really kind of
get this sense of this both the both
Heidegger's kind of pointing out what
metaphysics both realizes yet hides like
conceals at the same time there's
something about this where because it's
funny when I when we thought like that
well what's that
what's the medium well the what is is
the apprehension realization of
everything that's in a relationship with
it having being the thing that it's
relating it's like it yes he then it
ends up outside while seeing itself
inside but deeper and deeper and deeper
and deeper where there's no this is
where I was starting to kind of feel
like the realization of the emptiness
right there's no thing there there is
because it's it's it's that which makes
thinking as possible yeah right yeah and
notice how the relevance realization is
no thickness right because the one thing
you can't actually bring into the frame
is the framing anything you bring into
the frame as as if it was the framing
it's it's it's Jake you know it's James
is I I me you're always on there looking
at the me you can't look at the eye
through the eye Yeah right there's that
and notice that relevance realization is
always simultaneously distance closing
and concealing because I'm finding a
subset of the world relevant and that's
shining to me but I'm also finding
although I'm not finding in fact I'm not
even if I was noticing it I would hit
comma declare explosion I know I
intelligently ignorant a vast aspect of
the world or else I couldn't function
relevance realization is always a
revealing that is a concealer
that's why it's always evolving because
whatever there is no essence to the
revelation there's no nothing comes up
in the revelation that captures right
relevance forever it can't work that way
because it's always a concealing as well
as the revealing it then has to open up
to what was concealed and reveal again
and then open up to what was concealed
and revealed again and then again and
again and again and this is this is soul
this is dyin Oya right this is the
attempt the never completed all attempt
to disclose the intelligibility of the
world which is commodore charlie
explosive through time and that's what
we're doing well i'm just kind of just
i'm just feeling like a little couple of
things I'm feeling the virtue of
reverence right at play here in a plane
right now in the conversation it's like
you just can't there's something about
this sense of realizing that this kind
of what's doing the looking what's doing
the talking what's doing the perceiving
is the thing perceived on multiple
levels going up is that it's like
there's that it's like reverence almost
comes to a like to a peak like awareness
of finitude and limitation but the
Infinity yes sir so that's your
Holland's book finally amazing reverence
right yeah but I was thinking kind of
cleitus right listen not to me but to
the logos in my speech all things are
one right that's the reverence and it's
yeah again we talked about that that
movement of relevance realization if
it's caught up in the virtue of
reverence that's when you start to
realize the trajectory in the
transforming the trajectory and the
transformation that stands towards the
one but can never get there but that's
great
yeah cuz if we could get there we we
wouldn't be who we are and the world
wouldn't be what it is
yeah boy what a thing to revere not
having great like like it's like it's
like it's to Revere what brings it in
reverence is that I can't get there but
what the can't get there reveals it's
there
the way it's there right that's actually
yeah so Robert Browning a make ends meet
should exceed his grasp or what is a
heaven for this is why I think it's like
whatever this is like the two fingers
right of this of the essence right where
Michelangelo into painting that painting
was off before it's a thing you think
about this is before before the like the
re-emergence in a conscious way of the
Greeks right of the Medicis right it's
like that's all coming up you know
they're digging it out and like Marcio
Fujino and the like the the neoplatonist
right what's that yeah they're always
pointing down yep right yes right and I
hope that painting right there every
single part of it is telling a story I
don't know what the whole story is you
see eros in there and you see absolutely
the the how was I gonna say I was like
oh yes the chief fingers about it it's
like before that right it was always
depicted of like we're kind of God is
this kind of distant patriarch and man
is this kind of meagerly
right yearning for God and all of a
sudden in this it's like Vance is barely
like barely dawning to consciousness and
here's God right with all the angels
like and and they don't touch right and
if you know
right it's like if those if the if they
touch no one would reconcile that is
that divine kind of tension right that
is so and in and of course even the
movie they talk about like you know it's
talked about is the agony and the
ecstasy yes alright and I think what
we're talking about is that there's in
some way you know like you can almost
kind of make it kind of make a poster of
this right of where it's like agony or
ecstasy what's the difference that makes
the difference right and I think this is
what we're getting at I think the
difference is is something about that
thing that you said which is the one
right you don't want you don't want to
achieve the one right because it
wouldn't be the one that not like that
that aspiration that reverent aspiration
of like that I think that's the debt
that difference between the be the
experience of agony and the experience
of ecstasy with this right and I think
maybe
dialo goes constantly exemplifies that
right yeah I think so
I think the aporia's and deal logos are
the are the space that keeps the
reverence and attention alive yeah but
the whole trajectory is the sense it's
like it's an awesome Tony it's I mean I
always got the sense in Michelangelo
like it's an asymptote that there's a
perpetual closing but it'll never touch
ever right right right
absolutely absolutely how else would
creatures in prime get any intimation of
eternity there's no other way if they
get closure
that's not eternity that's that's an
idol in something that's finite alright
and if they but if there was no sense of
moving closer this is the epic pieces
right of the Eastern Orthodox some of
these are other birth fathers
perpetual affordance of
self-transcendence you genuinely step
transcending but you will never complete
it you will never give because creatures
that are in time only realize the truth
of the eternal truths in ongoing
transcendence right totally
yeah and that comes into like this is
where I think you know that like God is
a dhow it's a it's a metaphor makes
sense right because it's there's that
quality of just when you get to know a
person right there's like there is that
quality of like when you genuinely get
to know a person which is also the
realization of your own shadow is
simultaneously the recognition oh yeah
right like because you like in the in
the it's always been that thing about
how do you learn how to listen well
first you got a you got to realize that
you don't right the moment you realize
you don't is when listening but that's a
beautiful example of what I'm talking
about the Union idea that we can only
know the shadow ultimately or right
initially and ultimately only
biologically right it's only I cannot I
it's very hard for me to see how I'm
projecting unless I'm in dialogue with
somebody and that point you just made
that's brilliant because when you reject
my projection right you are an enacted
aporia that then it gives me the
opportunity for realizing the projection
and in realizing the projection I begin
in that way to get a sense of my shadow
and I think that's that Union idea
that's why Chris is writing in our
anthology that you're contributing to as
well right hit the second chapter he and
I are writing I should say he's first
author on writing it together about the
union practice as an instance of
Villalobos because exactly this idea and
there were people have gotten too
romantic about young in a sense they
they only sort of think about young age
psychically yeah right but yeah they
forget that young is presupposing that
all of this is taking place in a
therapeutic dialogic context right
that's the frame in which here yeah yeah
yeah that that it's only in something
like therapeutic dialogue that you can
genuinely become aware of the shadow
yeah absolutely
and like you yeah exactly and that's
that quality but that connection between
the vow peeks through right in those
moments of where it's like where my
projection of you or my my projection
onto you and this is what's interesting
it is one of the things I've noticed in
circles and in working with people in
this way is a lot of times were things
it's the beginning of a big of a big
kind of realization it's this sense of
where I always thought about I really
like the way that objects relations
psychology talks about it like there's
the objective pole like yourself or the
the self is actually always object
subject pole with with a binding level
of a fad and where people kind of like
will go on rants right we're all of a
sudden you're talking about like and
they'll just start addressing a concern
that I don't have that I didn't bring
that right but they're talking about it
as if they're in response and you can
start to tune into that stuff and then
you go like a so many times it's like
who are you talking to right there yeah
it in all that moment in that moment
there's this and if they really that
catch themselves in it like oh who am i
talk and it opens the question right and
that begins yes moment that they realize
that they weren't relating to the world
objectively if you will as it was they
were impacted than you realize but then
that you know begins this whole process
of disclosure great work yeah that's
important it's so this quality of love
it of how that one folds for us it it's
interesting to think about that this is
where it's like relationship in it I
mean this is
we're indistinguishable from our so our
sociality are you know it's like all the
way down but that sense of that sense of
the of the realization of myself is is
is allows that the realization of the
other the bow
right yeah that's right I mean in that
you can get that an Alexia is the Lexi
oh but it has to sort of you if you're
reading for transformation the Battle of
the text has that right yeah it has to
sort of catch you and lead you beyond
but I'm also thinking practically what
you just said was really important part
of what like what I was describing is
the amplification process is for the
amplifier to maybe periodically ask who
are you talking to right now
yeah that's very good I want to know
that now yeah I don't mean to turn away
from the camera that's great okay that's
good and it's it's a way and it's that
you gotta feel that question where it
yeah that where that question oh yeah
you could pretty much you could pretty
much ask that at any point and sometimes
the answer is gonna be you like and
sometimes it's gonna be like oh it's
just oh I was talking to the person
that's gonna get me in trouble at a tea
poit
right like I guess what happens with
like a lot of trauma like what ends up
with a lot of trauma it's those things
those structures become something that
like haunts people around right with
their constant relating it to break this
brings up an aspect that I write that's
brilliant
that was mean the to person the past
which I can't teach in the class
goodness then maybe I'll get geez now
what you do is you don't you sit you
feel that it's like I'm you'll see how
along to the full family of circling and
all the right you sit and
you do for passing it individually with
somebody present your visual field and
then one person is going to be the
speaker and then the other person is
going to be the amplify mirror as part
of where I got this idea
yeah but what the speaker does is they
when they're speaking to the mirror they
are talking to somebody else it's like
the empty chair so they talk to you so
you deliberately project you project it
onto your diet and and and and the the
person that's receiving they're supposed
to be and this is a really sweet spot
you have to be as fully present as
possible that while also being is
nonreactive yeah so that the person can
play out the projection but play it out
right and then and then you switch roles
and then I switch roles that you keep
doing that yes this is a way of getting
that in there uh what are you talking to
you right now when you can't be greater
that's very good thank you that yeah
totally and it's it's also there's a
sense in in a way that's not like
there's the projection catching but
there's also this sense of and I started
to notice this too this has been
something that started articulate like
when you're listening to something what
is it to really listen to somebody and
get yeah it's it's like when it's when
you start to notice the possibility that
is that there that's organizing their
attention right it's like that sense of
like what's glowing beyond the horizon
because if you think about it there is
that sense that every fucking everything
that I do is is impregnated with a
something's possible right this tailee
otic sense of it right and so getting
some isn't listing out what they just
said it's actually kind of getting what
is it that they are so like that's
beyond the horizon that they it it's
it's the thing that's constituting their
very being right and that when that yeah
lit up that's the experience of being
gotten right of like or that
experiencing like oh my god I'm totally
seen it's like you see
the possibility that that that I can't
that everything that I'm I am is in
relationship with right
they impregnated by but I'm so but don't
that's interesting I think that's very
convergent how I've been trying to
answer that same question I think I'm
really listening to somebody when I'm
catching their relevance realization
yeah well there's a contagion well I
like like like when we talk about
emotional contagion but its relevance
realization contagion yeah
and so red right I I no longer outside
of your world I mean it because like
your relevance realization is to some
degree be not represented in me it's
literally being instantiated yeah yeah
absolutely
cuz it's like it's so I mean we are so
few chiral it's like it's it's we are so
few chiral like just everything about
announces this you know this ecstatic
sense of time right yes and also that
quality of just that sense of when
somebody I mean it's happening and I
think it happens on multiple levels to
of just like there's the personal rest
like about my own character or something
like that right but then there's like
recognition these meta things when when
you get something there's a way where oh
my god something became possible but
what lights up is you go back right and
you reconfigure that posture you breed
impregnated that possibility all through
all the way through your history we
think all new narrative right yeah in
that sense of I think we're always doing
that on some level and where it gets
fixed right in stuck right or are the
are the places where where we get stuck
right it's no sense I agree
so I have unfortunately I have to get
going okay
I was wonderful is really wonderful
thank you so much John yes thank you guy
and I'd like to if you could send her
the files again I will
channel you got it you upload it on
yours first uploaded on mine what should
we call this one well I don't know I
think I think what we were moving
between talking about the dialectic yeah
talking about the logos we're moving
between talking about the practice and
talking about the process that's
realized I would call it something like
dialectic into the illumos yeah all
right sounds good to me
okay awesome thank you